Guide to the Henry Killam Murphy Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Killam Murphy papers
1899-1938
MS 231
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
369.75
(118 boxes)
The papers consist of architectural drawings, project files, photographs, correspondence, and ephemera documenting Henry Killam Murphy, particularly in his roles as a founding partner in the New Haven firm Murphy & Dana, and the New York City firm Murphy, McGill & Hamlin.
Murphy, Henry Killam, 1877-1954
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by accession.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alexander K. Murphy, 1979, 2002; and Janet (Mrs. William W.) Gaines, 1987-1988, 1990. Gift of the Wisconsin Historical Society, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated material: John Killam Murphy Papers (MS 1402), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Records created by Henry Killam Murphy and his related firms can be found in the Talbot Hamlin Papers and Architectural Records, 1880-1959, held by the Avery Drawings and Archives Collections at Columbia University.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Killam Murphy was born on August 19, 1877, in New Haven, Connecticut. After graduating from Yale College in 1899, Murphy spent a year in the Yale Graduate School preparing for a career as an architect. In 1900 he studied design in the Atelier Masqueray and then worked for the firm of Tracy and Startwout, architects. In 1907, he opened his own firm, and in 1908, took Richard Dana as a partner. Together Murphy and Dana designed entire colleges, private residences, libraries, office buildings, schools, churches, and other buildings, both in the United States and abroad. A substantial number of these were in China, including the development of a Changsha campus for the Yali Middle School and Hsiang-Ya Medical School built by the Yale Foreign Ministry Society (now Yale-China). After Dana left the firm in 1921, the firm continued as Murphy, McGill, & Hamlin until 1924 when Murphy began his own practice. Enamored of Chinese architecture, Murphy continued to do work in China. In 1928 he was appointed advisor to the National Government of the Republic of China and by 1929 was architect for city planning of Nanking. Murphy died on October 12, 1954, in Branford, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of architectural drawings, project files, photographs, correspondence, and ephemera documenting Henry Killam Murphy, particularly in his roles as a founding partner in the New Haven firm Murphy & Dana, and the New York City firm Murphy, McGill & Hamlin.
Other Finding Aids
For a list of projects and the boxes in which project materials are located, please consult the Project Index.
Architecture -- Designs and plans; Architecture; Asia; Architects; Murphy, Henry Killam, 1877-1954
- Inventory, 1899-1938
  - Personal and professional papers
    - Clippings, Circa 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1900-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-9)
      - Murphy, Edna to Henry Killam Murphy, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Maps, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Memorabilia, Circa 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notes, 1925-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, 1919-1930s, undated (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
    - Printed material, 1899-1919 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Speeches and writings, 1918-1930 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - Topical
      - Boats and yachts (miscellaneous sketches), Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Murphy & Dana
        - Accounting records, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - Estimates of commissions and correspondence, 1915-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Lists of jobs and engagements, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - New York Athletic Club: New Rochelle Harbor Patrol duty, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Will and driver's license, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Project records, 1903-1930
    Other Finding Aids
    For a list of projects and the boxes in which project materials are located, please consult the Project Index.
    - 137 E. 66th Street, 1918
      Scope and Contents
      Job location: New York, NY
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Adams, F.M., 1913-1914
      Job location: Ridgefield, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 62)
    - Alaska Hospital: solarium, 1918
      Job location: Fort Yukon, AK
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Alaska Mission Buildings, 1914-1918
      - Drawings (Folder 8)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - The American College, 1922-1927
      Job location: Madura, India
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Sofia American Mission and Schools, 1925
      Job location: Sofia, Bulgaria
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
      - Watercolors (Folder 105)
    - Amoy University, 1921
      Job location: Amoy [Xiamen], China
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Anderson, J.L., 1912-1913
      Job location: New Canaan, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 40)
    - Andersonville Memorial, 1909
      Job location: Andersonville, GA
      - Drawings (Folder 54)
    - Anglo-Chinese College, 1918
      Job location: Foochow, China
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Army/Navy YMCA, 1924-1925
      Job location: Manila, Philippines
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Arnold, Lauren, 1925
      Job location: Westport, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 19)
    - Arrowsmith, Edith, 1921
      Job location: Christmas Cove, ME
      - Drawings (Box 3)
    - Asiatic Petroleum Company, 1919
      Job location: Tsinan-Fu, China
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Avery, Brainerd
      Job location: Middletown Springs, VT
      - Drawings (Box 3)
    - Bashford Hall
      Job location: Yenching, China
      - Photographs (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Baur House, 1911-1912
      Job location: New Haven, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 68)
    - Bennet House, 1910-1911
      - Drawings (Folder 100)
    - Bowers, E.A., 1911
      - Drawings (Folder 17)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Bradley Plot (F.T.), 1910-1911
      - Drawings (Folder 42)
    - Bridgeport residence, 1910
      Job location: Bridgeport, CT
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Brighton Mills Housing Development, 1916
      Job location: Allwood, NJ
      - Drawings (Box 3)
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Brown, R.A., 1910-1917
      - Drawings (Folder 14)
    - Bryant, T.W., 1909-1911
      Job location: Torrington, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 20)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Bull, F.K., 1917
      Job location: Litchfield, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 103)
    - Cabell, Hartwell, 1918-1920
      - Drawings (Folder 22)
    - Cadillac Hotel, 1922
      Job location: Detroit, MI
      - Drawings (Folder 45)
    - Canton Christian College, 1924-1926
      Job location: Canton, China
      - Drawings (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Canton City Plan, 1919-1922
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Captain Cooke Panorama, 1917
      - Drawings (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Center Church
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Chamberlain, J.P., 1921
      - Drawings (Folder 96)
    - Changsha Yale College and Hospital [aka Ya-Li, aka Yale-in-China, 1917-1930
      Job location: Changsha, China
      - Drawings (Box 4)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Chappell, H.W., 1913-1914
      - Drawings (Box 3)
    - Childs, R.S., 1919
      Job location: Stamford, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 52)
    - Chinese group of houses
      Job location: Coral Gables, FL
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
      - Watercolors (Folder 108)
    - Cho-sen Christian College, 1918-1921
      Job location: Seoul, Korea
      - Photographs (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
      - Watercolors (Folder 106, Folder 108)
    - College of New Rochelle, 1912-1921
      Job location: New Rochelle, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 83)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Congregational Church, 1918-1920
      Job location: Cheshire, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 9)
    - Cooke, A.W., 1920
      Job location: Cooperstown, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 79)
    - Curtis Co., 1918
      Job location: Clinton, IA
      - Drawings (Folder 84)
    - Dana, R.H., 1911
      - Drawings (Box 2)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Danforth, F. S., 1911
      Job location: Orient, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 56)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Davidge, W.H., 1914-1915
      Job location: Weston, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 97)
    - Day, Harry G., 1915
      - Drawings (Folder 65)
    - Day, Julius, 1916-1917
      - Drawings (Folder 75)
    - Deforest, C.S., 1909-1910
      - Drawings (Folder 85)
    - Derby Neck Library, 1906-1913
      Job location: Derby, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 72)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Dollar, Robert Co. Building, 1919-1920
      Job location: Shanghai, China
      - Drawings (Box 3)
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Donaldson, R.D., 1921
      Job location: Montclair, NJ
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Driggs House, 1917
      Job location: Waterbury, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 91)
    - East Hampton, 1920
      Job location: East Hampton, NY
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Ethel Walker School, 1921-1925
      Job location: Hartford, CT
      - Drawings (Box 3)
      - Photographs (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - First Presbyterian, 1926
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Fisher Memorial Fireplace, 1921
      - Drawings (Folder 33)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Fitch Memorial Hospital
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - Foote, E.I., 1911
      - Drawings (Folder 48)
    - Foster, P.B., 1908-1909
      - Drawings (Folder 55)
    - Frick Estate, 1919
      Job location: Roslyn, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 53)
    - Fu Tan University, 1922-1924
      - Photographs (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Fukien Christian University, 1918
      - Drawings (Box 3, Folder 108)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
      - Watercolors (Folder 108)
    - Galpin, H.L., 1916
      - Drawings (Folder 50)
    - Georgia YMCA Building
      Job location: Augusta, GA
      - Drawings (Folder 25)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Ginling College, 1920-1924
      Job location: Nanking, China
      - Drawings (Box 3, Folder 90)
      - Photographs (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
      - Watercolors (Folder 109)
    - Golf and Country Club: Beach Club, 1917
      Job location: Great Neck, NY
      - Drawings (Box 3)
    - Government House, 1929
      - Drawings (Box 3)
    - Gray, A.E., 1909
      - Drawings (Folder 61)
    - Hall Memorial, Memorial Hall, Yale University, 1915
      - Drawings (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Hangchow College
      Job location: China
      - Drawings (Box 3, Folder 113)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Hanna, T.K., 1908
      Job location: Englewood, NJ
      - Drawings (Folder 26)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Herrick, J.B., 1921-1922
      Job location: Dorset, VT
      - Drawings (Folder 60)
    - Herwerden, J.V., 1918
      Job location: Rahway, NJ
      - Drawings (Folder 37)
    - Hopkins Grammar School, 1924-1928
      - Drawings (Box 3, Folder 101)
      - Photographs (Box 3)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Hopkins, C.R., 1914
      - Manuscript Material (Box 3)
    - Immergrun, 1916-1918
      Job location: Loretto, PA
      - Drawings (Folder 11)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - International Banking Corporation, 1917
      Job location: Peking, China
      - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Jefferson St. Boys Club, 1915
      - Drawings (Folder 21)
    - Journal Courier, 1912
      - Drawings (Folder 71)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Kelsey, S.T., 1915-1917
      Job location: East Orange, NJ
      - Drawings (Folder 94)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Kent, C.F., 1910-1911
      - Drawings (Folder 88)
    - Kimball, A.R., 1920
      - Drawings (Folder 32)
    - Kingsbury Arbor, 1917
      - Drawings (Folder 89)
    - Kitchel, C.P., 1914-1915
      - Drawings (Folder 16)
    - Koehn, W.H., 1916
      - Drawings (Folder 47)
    - Loomis Institute, 1912-1918
      Job location: Windsor, CT
      - Drawings (Box 4, Folder 34–35)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Lowry, John Jr., 1916
      - Drawings (Folder 86)
    - Lupton, R.M., 1918
      Job location: Mattituck, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 57)
    - Mayesville Industrial Institute, 1914-1916
      Job location: Mayesville, SC
      - Drawings (Folder 58)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Milford Town Hall Competition, 1915
      Job location: Milford, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 95)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Miller, G.P., 1916-1919
      - Drawings (Folder 30)
    - Moore, M.J., 1912
      Job location: Plainfield, NH
      - Drawings (Folder 63)
    - Murphy and Dana office, 1915
      - Drawings (Box 4)
    - Murphy McGill & Hamlin, 1923
      - Drawings (Folder 78)
    - Murphy, H.K., 1910
      Job location: Killam's Point, Branford, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 38)
    - Murphy, J.K., 1914
      - Drawings (Folder 64)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - New Britain State Normal School, 1920
      Job location: New Britain, CT
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - New Litchfield School Building, 1914
      - Drawings (Folder 23)
    - Oakville Housing Development, 1918
      Job location: Oakville, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 10)
    - Officer's Club, 1919-1920
      Job location: Quantico, VA
      - Drawings (Folder 13)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Osborne, Frances, 1906; 1910
      - Drawings (Folder 43)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Pacific Building, 1922
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Pardee, W.S., 1917
      - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Parish House, 1913-1914
      Job location: Bristol, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 31)
    - Pease and Elliman Agents
      - Drawings (Folder 67)
    - Peking Academy/Peking University, 1919-1920
      - Drawings (Box 4, Box 104, Folder 29)
      - Photographs (Box 104A)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
      - Watercolors (Folder 107)
    - Perry, Thomas
      - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Phelps, W. Lyon, 1908-1909
      - Drawings (Folder 6)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Pinchot, Amos, 1919-1920
      - Drawings (Folder 87)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Punch and Judy Theatre, 1914
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
      - Watercolors (Folder 110)
    - Putnam House Stairs, 1925
      Job location: Rye, NY
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Revolutionists' memorial, 1931-1935
      - Drawings (Box 4)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Russell, George P.
      Job location: White Plains, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 77)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Sabin, C.H., 1913
      - Drawings (Folder 39)
    - Scott, Donald, 1914-1916
      Job location: Cold Spring Harbor, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 36)
    - Scottish Rite Cathedral, 1923
      - Drawings (Box 4)
    - Security Insurance Company, 1923-1925
      - Drawings (Folder 12)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Seely, W.E., 1910-1911
      - Drawings (Folder 82)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Seymour Public Library, 1915
      Job location: Seymour, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 5)
    - Sheffield, Geo., 1909
      Job location: New London, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 27)
    - Slee, J.N.H., 1922-1923
      Job location: Fishkill Village, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 81)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Smith College
      Job location: Northampton, MA
      - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Solley House, 1916-1919
      Job location: Washington, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 76)
    - St. Alban's Housing Development, 1917
      Job location: St. Albans, WV
      - Drawings (Folder 24)
    - St. Andrew's Bay Club
      - Drawings (Folder 92)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - St. James Hospital, 1919
      Job location: Anking, China
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - St. Luke's Hospital Nurse's Home, 1911-1912
      Job location: Newburgh, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 66)
    - St. Luke's International Hospital, 1916-1918
      Job location: Tokyo, Japan
      - Drawings (Box 2)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - St. Mary's Hall, 1924
      - Photographs (Box 111)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - St. Paul's College, 1914-1922
      - Drawings (Box 4, Folder 99)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Shanghai College, 1919
      - Drawings (Box 4)
    - Solvay Workmen's Homes, 1917
      Job location: Syracuse, NY
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Stamford Woman's Club Inc., 1920
      - Drawings (Folder 41)
    - Sterling Memorial, American Legion, 1922
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Storrs Memorial Library, 1917
      Job location: Longmeadow, MA
      - Drawings (Folder 74)
    - Terry House, 1913
      - Drawings (Folder 7)
    - Thompson, M.D., 1920
      Job location: Elmira, NY
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Tillinghast, E.S., 1915
      - Drawings (Folder 51)
    - Treadway, T.G., 1914-1915
      - Drawings (Folder 44)
    - Trowbridge, E.Q., 1917
      Job location: Leete's Island, Branford, CT
      - Drawings (Folder 93)
    - Tsing Hua College, 1914-1922
      - Drawings (Folder 28)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4, Box 4B, Folder 4a)
    - U.S. Department of Labor Housing, 1918
      - Drawings (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Union College of the Philippines, 1920
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Union and New Haven Trust Co., 1925
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
      - Watercolors (Box 4)
    - United Workers' Boy's Club, 1915
      - Drawings (Folder 49)
    - Velasco Building, 1923
      - Drawings (Box 4)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Vermett, J.T. [possibly]
      Job location: Scarsdale, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 15)
    - Walker, H.W., 1920-1922
      - Drawings (Folder 80)
      - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Wallace, G.W., 1920-1921
      - Drawings (Folder 102)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Wayland Academy, 1918
      Job location: Hangchow, Chekiang, China
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Webster, The, 1903
      - Drawings (Folder 98)
    - West Boylston Mfg. Co., 1919
      Job location: Easthampton, MA
      - Drawings (Folder 59)
    - Wetmore House, 1907-1908
      Job location: Fort Salonga/ Northport, Long Island, NY
      - Drawings (Folder 73)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Whitehouse, N. R., 1920
      Job location: Newport, RI
    - Williams, F.W., 1915-1916
      - Drawings (Folder 70)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Williams, R.H., 1915
      - Drawings (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Woman's Municipal League of the City of New York, 1912-1915
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Yale Hope Mission, 1928
      - Drawings (Folder 46)
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Yenching University, 1926
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Yonkers High School (competition), 1921
      Job location: Yonkers, NY
      - Manuscript Material (Box 4)
    - Unidentified
      - Drawings (Box 4, Box 104C)
      - Photographs (Box 4, Box 104, Box 104B)
- Additional Material, 1904-1907, 1926-1928; Accession 1988-M-046
  Also includes Accession 1990-M-039.
  - Buccaneers Club
    - Agreements, bylaws, and constitution, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Bushey (Ira S.) and Sons, Inc., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Haight, Robert S., 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Hausmann, Frank, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Herring, Oswald C., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Hooper, Will Phil, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Parsons, Edgerton, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Titus, A. H., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Membership lists, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Memorabilia and clippings, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Oversize (Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Oversize, Blueprint of Barkentine "Buccaneer" of New York, undated (Folder 2)
  - Account book of architectural commissions, 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 13)